Phi Beta Kappa Records UA025
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Phi Beta Kappa Records
1920 -- 1977
1841 -- 1986
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Phi Beta Kappa
Miller, Russell E.
UA025
8.7 Linear Feet 7 boxes
Arrangement
This collection is organized in two series: Membership card catalog and Subject files.
Custodial History
Many of the records in this collections were originally part of the Activities and Organizations collection compiled by Russell Miller.
Scope and Contents
This collection document the activities of the Delta Chapter of Phi Beta Kappa (PBK) at Tufts University and consists of artifacts, the membership card catalog (up until 1978), and subject files. Significant topics in this collection include the recruitment and initiation of new Tufts University Phi Beta Kappa members.
Biographical / Historical
The Delta Chapter of Phi Beta Kappa (PBK), a national honorary society, was chartered on September 7, 1892, 1892 through the efforts of Thomas Wentworth Higginson, President of the United Chapters, Professor William R. Shipman, a member of the society at Middlebury College and the first librarian at Tufts, and Professor Frank Pierrepont Graves, a professor of classics while at Tufts and a member of the society at Columbia University - the year before the original chapter at the College of William and Mary was reactivated. The Tufts chapter was the fourth in the state to be established, and hence the designation "Delta." Nationally, women were first admitted to Phi Beta Kappa in 1875. Among the first cohort of women studying at Tufts, two were initiated into Phi Beta Kappa in 1896; there were a total of six initiates that year.
The PBK Executive Board of Delta Chapter at Tufts University elects students in the spring who show academic excellence in a wide array of disciplines, as well as intellectual commitment, originality and achievement in a particular area, and the quality of mind characteristic of a true scholar.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection contains some restricted material. Restrictions related to specific material are listed in the detailed contents list.
Student life; Student Activities -- Student Government, Clubs, and Organizations; Student life
- Membership Card Catalogue, 1841 -- 1978; UA025.001; 1.2 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  Cards are arranged by a color code indicating member status (charter members, faculty members, ongoing membership, deceased). Handwritten reference card lists the following categories, however white cards were also used for male members.T he original color code was explained in an index card, filed in-front of the alphabetical run Series 1, Item 1.
  White cards: Regular card. Maiden name of women used in filing order if unmarried at time of initiation. Brown/Yellow cards: Married Name of Women. Blue: Faculty. Pink: Honorary.
  Arrangement
  Cards are arranged by a color code indicating member status (charter members, faculty members, ongoing membership, deceased). Handwritten reference card lists the categories, however white cards were also used for male members.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Phi Beta Kappa Delta of Mass-Tufts Members in Course A-G, 1911 -- 1978; UA025.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
    Each membership card contains a variable number of elements. Elements present on nearly every card in this drawer: member's name (maiden name), address, date initiated, and graduation class year. Other less common elements are: graduation date, alternate written addresses, current status (current school year), Phi Beta Kappa degree date, date elected, maiden name, and husband's name. On the back of about half of the cards are a list of dates when a member paid dues.
  - Phi Beta Kappa Delta of Mass-Tufts Members in Course H-P, 1911 -- 1978; UA025.001.001.00002 (Box 1)
    Each membership card contains a variable number of elements. Elements present on nearly every card in this drawer include: member's name (maiden name), address, date initiated, and graduation class year. Other less common elements are: graduation date, alternate written addresses, current status (current school year), Phi Beta Kappa degree date, date elected, maiden name, and husband's name. On the back of about half of the cards are a list of dates when a member paid dues.
  - Phi Beta Kappa Delta of Mass-Tufts Members in Course Q-Z and Other member indices, 1911 -- 1978; UA025.001.001.00003 (Box 1)
    Member Lists:
    1) Regular Members, tabs Q-Z
    2) Student
    3) Honorary
    4) Faculty
    5) Fac. Retired ["Fac. Retired" is an abbreviation for "Faculty Retired."]
    6) Hon Dec, not Ch ["Hon Dec, not Ch" is probably an abbreviation for "Honorary Deceased, Not of Chapter."]
    The cards have only four elements: Name, Address, TU number, LOST date.
  - Other member indices, 1841 -- 1964; UA025.001.001.00004 (Box 1)
    1) Recently Deceased or Moved
    2) Phi Beta Kappa cards sent over from A.L. Parkman by H.Y. Schaejhe. The cards sent over from A.L. Parkman have only four elements: Name, Address, TU number, LOST date.
    3) Charter
    4) Honorary Dec'd. [Dec'd is an abbreviation of Deceased.]
    5) In Course Dec'd
    6) Deceased Members A-Z
  - Other member indices, 1841 -- 1964; UA025.001.001.00005 (Box 1)
    Predecessor of "Phi Beta Kappa Delta of Mass-Tufts Members in Course Members A-Z" [archivist created title] including less information and data elements than previous sections. It is arranged alphabetically without any additional tabs. The four main elements on each cards are: name, address, graduation class, and dues paid. There occasionally is a stamped date, which may be when the card was entered into the card catalog system, or when the member's address and details were updated.
- Subject Files, 1860 -- 1986; 1910 -- 1984; UA025.002; 7.2 Linear Feet
  This series contains include correspondence, student transcripts, meetings and minutes among other material. Historical records of Phi Beta Kappa were arranged chronologically at the beginning of the series, followed by an alphabetical run of subject files; ephemera included at the end.
  75 years from the date of creation.
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 1892 -- 1920; UA025.002.003.00001 (Box 3)
    Includes a published history of PBK titled 'Phi Beta Kappa: Delta of Massachusetts Tufts College ' (1910).
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 1921 -- 1940; UA025.002.003.00002 (Box 3)
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 1956 -- 1970; UA025.002.003.00003 (Box 3)
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 1941 -- 1955; UA025.002.003.00004 (Box 3)
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 1971 -- 1975; UA025.002.003.00005 (Box 3)
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 1976 -- 1986; UA025.002.003.00006 (Box 3)
  - Phi Beta Kappa: membership forms, 1860 -- 1900; UA025.002.003.00007 (Box 3)
    Membership forms include birth date and location, parents, education, degrees conferred, occupations, positions and offices held, societies joined, special lines of work pursued, and literary work, special and general.
  - Phi Beta Kappa membership logbook, 1913 -- 1923; UA025.002.003.00008 (Box 3)
  - Photographs, 1938 -- 1966; UA025.002.003.00009 (Box 3)
    Some photos undated.
  - Phi Beta Kappa, Treasurer's Records, 1893 -- 1897; UA025.002.003.00010 (Box 3)
  - Phi Beta Kappa, Treasurer's Records, 1916 -- 1920; UA025.002.003.00011 (Box 3)
  - Office correspondence scrapbook, 1897 -- 1929; UA025.002.003.00012 (Box 3)
  - Academic Standing - Candidates For Election, 1943 -- 1970; UA025.002.003.00013 (Box 3)
  - Bookkeeping Records, 1975 -- 1976; UA025.002.003.00014 (Box 3)
  - Bookkeeping Records, 1976 -- 1977; UA025.002.003.00015 (Box 3)
  - Bookkeeping Records, 1977 -- 1978; UA025.002.003.00016 (Box 3)
  - Bookkeeping Records, 1978 -- 1979; UA025.002.003.00017 (Box 3)
  - Bookkeeping Records, 1979 -- 1980; UA025.002.003.00018 (Box 3)
  - Bookkeeping Records, 1980 -- 1982; UA025.002.003.00019 (Box 3)
  - Bookkeeping - Phi Beta Kappa Dodge Fund, 1937 -- 1981; UA025.002.003.00020 (Box 3)
  - Bookkeeping - Phi Beta Kappa Ledger Book, 1951 -- 1980; UA025.002.003.00021 (Box 3)
  - Bookkeeping - Phi Beta Kappa Treasurers, 1952 -- 1969; UA025.002.003.00022 (Box 3)
  - Candidates - Fall, 1968; UA025.002.003.00023 (Box 3)
  - Candidates - Spring, 1969; UA025.002.003.00024 (Box 3)
  - Candidates - Fall, 1969; UA025.002.003.00025 (Box 3)
  - Candidates - Fall, 1970; UA025.002.003.00026 (Box 3)
  - Candidates - Spring, 1971; UA025.002.003.00027 (Box 3)
  - Candidates - Fall - Actions Taken, 1973; UA025.002.003.00028 (Box 3)
  - Candidates - December (1), 1978; UA025.002.003.00029 (Box 3)
  - Candidates - December (2), 1978; UA025.002.003.00030 (Box 3)
  - Candidates - December (3), 1978; UA025.002.003.00031 (Box 3)
  - Candidates - Spring, 1980; UA025.002.003.00032 (Box 3)
  - Candidates - Fall, 1980; UA025.002.003.00033 (Box 3)
  - Candidates - Spring - Bulk, 1981; UA025.002.003.00034 (Box 3)
  - Candidates - Spring, 1982; UA025.002.003.00035 (Box 3)
  - Candidates - Considered - Transcripts, 1967 -- 1973; UA025.002.004.00001 (Box 4)
  - Candidates - Considered - Spring, 1972; UA025.002.004.00002 (Box 4)
  - Candidates - Considered - Spring, 1973; UA025.002.004.00003 (Box 4)
  - Candidates - Elected - Fall, 1971; UA025.002.004.00004 (Box 4)
  - Candidates - Elected - Spring, 1972; UA025.002.004.00005 (Box 4)
  - Candidates - Elected - Fall - With Parents' Address, 1972; UA025.002.004.00006 (Box 4)
  - Candidates - Elected - Spring, 1973; UA025.002.004.00007 (Box 4)
  - Candidates - Elected - Fall - Transcripts, Local and Parents' Addresses, 1973; UA025.002.004.00008 (Box 4)
  - Candidates - Elected - Spring, 1974; UA025.002.004.00009 (Box 4)
  - Candidates - Elected - Fall, 1974; UA025.002.004.00010 (Box 4)
  - Candidates - Elected - Spring, 1975; UA025.002.004.00011 (Box 4)
  - Candidates - Elected - Fall, 1975; UA025.002.004.00012 (Box 4)
  - Candidates - Elected - June, 1976; UA025.002.004.00013 (Box 4)
  - Candidates - Exercises - Fall, 1983; UA025.002.004.00014 (Box 4)
  - Candidates - Not Elected - No Further Consideration - Fall, 1974; UA025.002.004.00015 (Box 4)
  - Candidates - Not Elected - No Further Action - Spring, 1975; UA025.002.004.00016 (Box 4)
  - Candidates - Not Elected - No Further Action - Fall, 1975; UA025.002.004.00017 (Box 4)
  - Candidates - Not Elected - May, 1976; UA025.002.004.00018 (Box 4)
  - Certificate and Key Orders - Fall and Spring, 1970; UA025.002.004.00019 (Box 4)
  - Certificate and Key Orders - Fall, 1971; UA025.002.004.00020 (Box 4)
  - Certificate and Key Orders - Spring, 1972; UA025.002.004.00021 (Box 4)
  - Certificate and Key Orders - Fall, 1972; UA025.002.004.00022 (Box 4)
  - Certificate and Key Orders, 1976 -- 1982; UA025.002.004.00023 (Box 4)
  - Certificates Not Picked Up, 1977; UA025.002.004.00024 (Box 4)
  - Chapter Membership - Entire, 1932 -- 1946; UA025.002.004.00025 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence - General, 1968 -- 1981; UA025.002.004.00026 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence - National - General, 1971 -- 1979; UA025.002.004.00027 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence - National - Speakers, 1974 -- 1976; UA025.002.004.00028 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence - Phi Beta Kappa - Fall, 1973; UA025.002.004.00029 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence - Speakers, 1974 -- 1980; UA025.002.004.00030 (Box 4)
  - Honorary Members, 1894 -- 1945; UA025.002.004.00031 (Box 4)
  - Interdepartmental Requisitions, 1980 -- 1982; UA025.002.004.00032 (Box 4)
  - Letterhead, UA025.002.004.00033 (Box 4)
  - Manuals - Delegates Manual, 1976; UA025.002.004.00034 (Box 4)
  - Manuals - Manual for Chapter Officers, 1959; UA025.002.004.00035 (Box 4)
  - Manuals - Secretary's Manual of Procedure, 1973; UA025.002.004.00036 (Box 4)
  - Meeting and Arrangements - Fall and Spring, 1971 -- 1972; UA025.002.004.00037 (Box 4)
  - Meetings - Meeting Agenda - Phi Beta Kappa - Annual Business Meeting, 1977; UA025.002.004.00038 (Box 4)
  - Meetings - Fall Meeting, 1978; UA025.002.004.00039 (Box 4)
  - Meetings - Spring Meeting, 1979; UA025.002.004.00040 (Box 4)
  - Meetings - Fall Meetings, 1979; UA025.002.004.00041 (Box 4)
  - Meetings - Spring Meeting, 1980; UA025.002.004.00042 (Box 4)
  - Meetings - Fall Meeting, 1980; UA025.002.004.00043 (Box 4)
  - Meetings - Fall and Spring Meetings, 1981 -- 1982; UA025.002.004.00044 (Box 4)
  - Meetings - Spring Meeting, 1983; UA025.002.004.00045 (Box 4)
  - Membership List, n.d., UA025.002.004.00046 (Box 4)
  - Membership List, Corrected to April 1948 and Minutes of Meetings, 1943 -- 1951; UA025.002.004.00047 (Box 4)
  - Membership Lists, Procedures, Instructions to Secretaries, 1979 -- 1983; UA025.002.004.00048 (Box 4)
  - Membership - Listings from National Files - October, 1979; UA025.002.004.00049 (Box 4)
  - Necrologist Reports, 1942 -- 1980; UA025.002.004.00050 (Box 4)
  - Office Form Letters, 1971 -- 1984; UA025.002.004.00051 (Box 4)
  - Ordering Supplies and Information, UA025.002.004.00052 (Box 4)
  - Phi Beta Kappa - Spring (1), 1977; UA025.002.004.00053 (Box 4)
    Transcripts
  - Phi Beta Kappa - Spring (2), 1977; UA025.002.004.00054 (Box 4)
  - Phi Beta Kappa - Spring (3), 1977; UA025.002.004.00055 (Box 4)
  - Phi Beta Kappa - Annual Address - Alpha Chapter of North Carolina, 1965; UA025.002.004.00056 (Box 4)
  - Phi Beta Kappa - Annual Address - Alpha Chapter of North Carolina, 1966; UA025.002.004.00057 (Box 4)
  - Phi Beta Kappa - Annual Address - Alpha Chapter of North Carolina, 1968; UA025.002.004.00058 (Box 4)
  - Phi Beta Kappa - Annual Report, 1982 -- 1983; UA025.002.004.00059 (Box 4)
  - Phi Beta Kappa - Arrangements - Building Sign-up - Directions for Initiates - Fall, 1972; UA025.002.004.00060 (Box 4)
  - Phi Beta Kappa - Bulletins, 1976 -- 1980; UA025.002.004.00061 (Box 4)
  - Phi Beta Kappa - Complete Run - March, 1979; UA025.002.004.00062 (Box 4)
  - Phi Beta Kappa - Extra Mailings for Spring, 1984; UA025.002.004.00063 (Box 4)
  - Phi Betta Kappa - Faculty and Staff List, 1940 -- 1979; UA025.002.004.00064 (Box 4)
  - Phi Beta Kappa - Initation Ritual - President's Copy, UA025.002.004.00065 (Box 4)
  - Phi Beta Kappa - Internal Revenue Service Correspondence/Papers, 1942 -- 1977; UA025.002.004.00066 (Box 4)
  - Phi Beta Kappa - Key Order and Key Prices, 1974 -- 1977; UA025.002.004.00067 (Box 4)
  - Phi Beta Kappa - Massachusetts Sales Tax, 1970 -- 1979; UA025.002.004.00068 (Box 4)
  - Phi Beta Kappa - Membership Certificate Order Form - Blank, UA025.002.004.00069 (Box 4)
  - Phi Beta Kappa - Preparation Folder - Fall, 1972; UA025.002.004.00070 (Box 4)
  - Phi Beta Kappa - Recommendations - Fall Elections, 1971; UA025.002.004.00071 (Box 4)
  - Phi Beta Kappa - Recommendations - Spring, 1972; UA025.002.004.00072 (Box 4)
  - Phi Beta Kappa - Spring Arrangements, 1972; UA025.002.004.00073 (Box 4)
  - Phi Beta Kappa - Spring Arrangements - May 2nd, 1973; UA025.002.004.00074 (Box 4)
  - Phi Beta Kappa - Work Folder - Spring, 1970; UA025.002.004.00075 (Box 4)
  - Phi Beta Kappa - Work Folder - Spring, 1971; UA025.002.004.00076 (Box 4)
  - Phi Beta Kappa - Work Folder, Letters - Spring, 1972; UA025.002.004.00077 (Box 4)
  - Phi Beta Kappa - Work Folder - Letters to Executive Committee, Members of Delta Chapter, Faculty, Parents, Initiates - Fall, 1972; UA025.002.004.00078 (Box 4)
  - Phi Beta Kappa - Work Folder - Fall, 1973; UA025.002.004.00079 (Box 4)
  - Phi Beta Kappa - Work Folder [Archivist Created Heading], 1979 -- 1984; UA025.002.005.00001 (Box 5)
  - Phi Beta Kappa - Work Folder - Fall, 1982; UA025.002.005.00002 (Box 5)
  - Phi Beta Kappa - Work Folder - Spring, 1983; UA025.002.005.00003 (Box 5)
  - Photographic Negatives, n.d., UA025.002.005.00004 (Box 5)
  - Policies and Procedures - Local, 1970 -- 1980; UA025.002.005.00005 (Box 5)
    Also contains programs from meetings, 1970-1980
  - Policies and Procedures - National, 1961 -- 1977; UA025.002.005.00006 (Box 5)
  - Preliminary Letter to Chairmen of Departments, Members of L.A., and Jackson Faculty - Spring, 1972; UA025.002.005.00007 (Box 5)
  - Procedures File - Outline, n.d., UA025.002.005.00008 (Box 5)
  - Purchase Orders - Bulk, 1982; UA025.002.005.00009 (Box 5)
  - Reports to National Office, 1940 -- 1975; UA025.002.005.00010 (Box 5)
  - Romanell-Phi Beta Kappa Professorship, 1982; UA025.002.005.00011 (Box 5)
  - Speakers - Phi Beta Kappa Visiting Scholars - S. Fred Singer, 1981; UA025.002.005.00012 (Box 5)
  - Transcripts - Fall - Elected Candidates, 1971; UA025.002.005.00013 (Box 5)
  - Transcripts - Spring- Candidates Considered, 1972; UA025.002.005.00014 (Box 5)
  - Transcripts - Fall- Candidates Considered, 1972; UA025.002.005.00015 (Box 5)
  - Transcripts (1), 1974; UA025.002.005.00016 (Box 5)
  - Transcripts (2), 1974; UA025.002.005.00017 (Box 5)
  - Transcripts - October, 1979; UA025.002.005.00018 (Box 5)
  - Transcripts - Spring, 1980; UA025.002.005.00019 (Box 5)
  - Transcripts - Fall, 1980; UA025.002.005.00020 (Box 5)
  - Transcripts - Spring (1), 1981; UA025.002.005.00021 (Box 5)
  - Transcripts - Spring (2), 1981; UA025.002.005.00022 (Box 5)
  - Transcripts - Spring (3), 1981; UA025.002.005.00023 (Box 5)
  - Transcripts - Spring, 1982; UA025.002.005.00024 (Box 5)
  - Transcripts (1), 1983; UA025.002.005.00025 (Box 5)
  - Transcripts (2), 1983; UA025.002.005.00026 (Box 5)
  - Transcripts (3), 1983; UA025.002.005.00027 (Box 5)
  - United Chapters of Phi Beta Kappa, 1970 -- 1981; UA025.002.005.00028 (Box 5)
  - Visiting Scholar Program, 1982 -- 1983; UA025.002.005.00029 (Box 5)
  - Phi Beta Kappa plaque and embosser, 1955; UA025.002.005.00030 (Box 5)
    Plaque is engraved with the generic name of John Doe, and dated February 19th, 1955.
  - Charles W. Parmenter's Phi Beta Kappa Key, UA025.002.005.00031 (Box Shared 9)
  - J.T. Farnsworth Phi Beta Kappa Key, 1873; UA025.002.005.00032 (Box Shared 9)
  - Phi Beta Kappa Key, Charles W. Parmenter, 1893; UA025.002.005.00033 (Box Shared 16)
    Parmenter, class of 1877, was elected to PBK in 1893.